<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Illness to Ultra</title>
    <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Illness to Ultra</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 19:29:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.illnesstoultra.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Health Improvements</title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/healthImprovements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/healthImprovements/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;everyone-has-issues:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;Everyone has issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone in the world has some health issue/s. Just some more than others. But just because we think we feel ok, it doesn’t mean we should stop looking for solutions to improve our health. We often answer the question “How are you?” with “Good” , “Ok , “Yeah, not bad” and only sometimes we say we are feeling “down and out” or react in some negative way. Often this is not the true representation of how we feel, it’s just the amount we want to divulge. So I’d like to force people to review and ask themselves a question, “How could I feel even better?” This question has no baseline. It just encourages you to seek more from yourself than what you currently have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-back-story:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;The Back Story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this blog name suggests, I had a strange bout of illness in which I was unsure of the cause. I also went to a bunch of doctors in different countries and still was none the wiser. The only hope I believed I had was that my body would reset to my known equilibrium and therefore wait. This method did work but only to a certain extent, I improved, but very slowly. Maybe this was because my issue was difficult to get rid of or maybe I just wasn’t tackling it in the right way. I don’t want to get into the specifics in this post as I believe it is fairly irrelevant unless your body is exactly the same as mine, instead I want to focus on what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-to-listen-to:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;Who to listen to?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy answer, “Everyone and no one”. In the early stages the only hope I believed I had was in doctors, but with hindsight this was incorrect. I believed there were many errors made by doctors (I’m not saying it’s their fault, the healthcare system is also not built up to help doctors do their job), and even some out right scary propositions where made. If I had 100% brain power at the time I would have reverted back to my University days and researched as much as possible. One thing that has come of this is that I can safely still side with being sceptical until you’ve researched and understand your situation. Back to the answer of this question. We need to listen to everyone as we can be informed by many different sources. One of my “aha” moments came from a podcast. I’m not saying that that was the solution, but it got me thinking in a different way. Do the research and read in depth into the issues, work as hard as you can to become a master in the field. Because your situation is so specific it’s possible to become a master in yourself and nobody knows you better that YOU!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;don-t-settle-for-ok:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;Don’t settle for OK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After six months of very gradual improvements I started coming round to the idea that I would never feel 100% again. I’d settled for second best and started looking to other areas of my life which could satisfy me. This is a mental attitude which needs to be quashed! You can be better, even if it’s 1%, that is still better, and you never know, the next year you may be another 1% better. If you keep searching for answers you will find new avenues. Personally I’d found some amazing correlations between my health and information that you would find with what I would call modern healthcare. Modern healthcare is looking to your past and matching exploring effects which can be seen in your current state, be it labs, subjective feelings, or other tests. I’d never explored into my past health history as much as I did at this time. It brought up some amazing findings and links to possible historical mistakes. It also took the focus off the “symptom of the day”, which is what many other doctors would always focus on. This would lead doctors to use some metaphorical sledgehammer to solve the problem. We delveled into underlying problems and attempted to solve these in the assumption that this would push my body into balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-the-next-step:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;What’s the next step?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple. Keep on searching. Just because I feel better on most days it doesn’t mean I don’t have off days. This means I can still further improve and this fact will not change for the rest of my life. My research has pushed me further into genetics, which has brought up some very interesting results in which I can act upon now to bring a better life in the future. This type of information is not in mainstream medicine yet, and maybe some would say a little experimental, but scientific papers and study groups are the best and only information we have to work on. Plus the data I have found in my genetics has further backed up my lab tests and symptoms I’ve had throughout the last 4 years of my life. I feel this indicates some great evidence in which to act upon.  Again the action here is to keep searching and backup your theories with evidence. Try not to be irrational, and do not take everyones opinion and information as gospel. Ensure you backup any information with your own evidence and ensure you understand the situation before you act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:bdfbc040aad2a9be7d416ca4ef522d6f&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out to write this blog post about the specific information and data I’d found on my health issues. But after the first sentence I decided to write a different blog post. What’s the use in knowing my issues? I hope I’d encourage you to research your own issues. And again, you may not even have issues. If you don’t, just research ways in which to improve your life. These improvements can come in all walks of life, being it mental, physical, emotional. It doesn’t really matter, but anything you can do to learn more about yourself will benefit you in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your body exhausted?</title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/isYourBodyExhausted/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/isYourBodyExhausted/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to draw upon my recent experiences and explore the ways we can analyse if our bodies actually need extra rest. When this happened to me, I took a step back from training to analyse how I really felt and have now adjusted my training plan based on these findings, which I will discuss in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-you-really-depleted:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Are you really depleted?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the major question of the article. It is common for our brain to trick us into thinking that we are really tired and are unable to complete the next training session. Often this is not the case and the best thing to do is to go out there and defeat your brain. As I mentioned in my other posts, I do not suffer from this too much and I have a tendency to overtrain. Even when I feel tired, I believe it&amp;rsquo;s still possible to go out there and do my training. But the question remains; Is the fatigue, my brain or my body?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;heart-rate-variance:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Heart Rate Variance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/hrvGraph.png&#34; alt=&#34;hrv&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve not read my last blog about &lt;a href=&#34;http://illnesstoultra.com/blog/hrv&#34;&gt;heart rate variance&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;d suggest giving it a quick read to see if you could incorporate it in your routine. If you are unsure of what your body signals are trying to tell you, HRV can be a great indicator to help make sense of these signals. HRV will allow you to see a representation of stress on your body. HRV is an optimal measurement, as it is not subjective like your thoughts. However, there are downfalls to HRV measurements. If you are mentally stressed, this can have an adverse effect on the readings and potentially mask the real issues. Using HRV is a great guide to help you understand your bodies physical state, but should not be relied upon as the sole source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;injuries:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Injuries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One point to be aware of is the risk of injuries. This is another difficult and very subjective area in which it is possible to find excuses not to train. It&amp;rsquo;s important to know that injury is possible if you overtrain. There are many reasons for this, but one factor is that after your initial training session, your muscles are still in a state of recovery and are not able to work at 100%. This  can cause an imbalance and push stress onto other parts of the body. It is at this point that joints can suffer and muscle failure could occur. How do we know we are going to get injured? This is a subjective analysis, but I often notice how stiff I become after a training session. If I have a smaller range of motion than normal, I am more likely to injure myself. My stride and gait will change slightly to accommodate this decreased motion, which will result in undue stress on the different muscles that are now working.  If you feel confident that your stiffness would dissipate during your run, then I would say it is probably safe for you to train. This is often the case after a long run or workout session, but once the blood starts flowing throw the muscles, they are warmed up and able to perform close to 100%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;be-subjective-and-use-data:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Be subjective and use data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/trainingLog.png&#34; alt=&#34;training log&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good way of analysing why you could be deleted of energy is to look for patterns in data that you have collected. This can be as simple as having a quick look at your training log and finding a correlation. But there are many other aspects to analyse. For example, suffering  from an illness, lack of sleep, mental stress or anything else could affect your will to train. It&amp;rsquo;s really important to throw your emotional thoughts aside during this task and attempt to come to a logical conclusion. I find that tracking as much data as possible allows me to browse through my history and attempt to find patterns which may be causing issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;real-world-example:d5a31d1a760a4984ae4214106400a398&#34;&gt;Real world example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I encountered a situation in which I used all the method mentioned previously to fully understand what decision to make. The situation started after playing football for the first time in 2 years. Again, I don&amp;rsquo;t like doing things by half, so I ran around like a mad man for an hour and my body really took a beating. The next morning my HRV results were poor?, as can be seen in the image below.
&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/hrvOverworked.png&#34; alt=&#34;hrv overworked&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data shown in the HRV reading is clearly showing that I have far less energy to expend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three days following the football I was very stiff and my range of motion was drastically reduced. Therefore I was at high risk of injury if I attempted any further exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally, I knew that I had been playing football the day before, so with this data it was understandable why I was feeling depleted of energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of all of this, I missed two training sessions which included an interval session and a long run. I was not too concerned with the intervals as the football substituted for this very well. But I chose to miss the long run as a result of being too stiff. I was confident that my stride and gait would have been affected and would increase my chances of  injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time I know to tone it down at football, but also ensure I have a rest day scheduled the day after, along with easy training days the two days after. Overall, this was an enlightening experience and a great way to account for unforseen aspects affecting my training schedule and counteract it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heart rate variance</title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/hrv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/hrv/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-heart-rate-variance:710fa11f4f3f3f0cce2973e996c8d4f3&#34;&gt;What is Heart Rate Variance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heart rate variance (HRV) is based on the measurement of time between heart beats. This measure mean is named the R-R interval. Having timings which are more variable gives a higher HRV and vise versa. Most people will know their resting heart rate, or at least understand what heart rate represents. But it may come as a surprise that the timing of the heart rate is not metronomic. There are tiny fluctuations in these R-R intervals, which can be used as a great indicator of fitness and stress on the body and this is what we are going to further explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/hrvGraph.png&#34; alt=&#34;Picture of R-R interval&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-does-this-tell-us:710fa11f4f3f3f0cce2973e996c8d4f3&#34;&gt;What does this tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to analyse HRV, but in it&amp;rsquo;s most simplistic approach, the higher your HRV the better. But this does not tell the full story. When the body has been stressed and is recovering, for example, the morning after a hard workout, the R-R interval becomes a lot more rhythmic, therefore lowering HRV. This is true of any stressful situation on the body, whether it be recovery from training, illness or even food allergies; essentially anything that can stress your body. So in the inverse to this, when the body is truly rested, the R-R interval becomes much more sporadic and HRV goes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this information we can find the optimal time to train without questioning our subjective thoughts. From here we can tune our training plans and also look for trends in the data to further our performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-we-test-this:710fa11f4f3f3f0cce2973e996c8d4f3&#34;&gt;How do we test this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/polarHRM.png&#34; alt=&#34;Polar Heart Rate Monitor&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring HRV is fairly simple, although it takes patience and consistency. One of the biggest issues to understand is that HRV values are personalized, therefore we should not compare scores with one another as everybody&amp;rsquo;s baseline is very different. In addition to this, it is really important to work out a baseline value before amending training routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To perform the measurements, a standard fitness heart rate monitor will be needed. Although smartwatches often have HR functionality, they are not accurate enough to gather this information.  Therefore, a chest mounted monitor is recommended. Next we&amp;rsquo;ll need a mobile application which kicks off the measurement and aggregates the data. I&amp;rsquo;ve found &lt;a href=&#34;https://elitehrv.com/&#34;&gt;Elite HRV&lt;/a&gt; to be the easiest and most reliable product for this. Just follow the guidelines in the app and it will take you through the measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the first week, the algorithm will be tuning itself to your data, so it&amp;rsquo;s important to stay consistent. To ensure that there are no external effects skewing your measure, it is best to take the measurement in the morning just after you wake up. This ensures the body is in its most rested state and that factors like food, or mental stress have not had an effect on the measurement. Another point to make is the position in which to take the measurement. It&amp;rsquo;s been referenced in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mtXzlFytJnw&amp;amp;t=3s&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; that it is ideal to take the measurement whilst sitting and resting in a chair. Some applications show that it is best to take the measurement whilst lying down, but this has been seen to suppress the response and render it hard to extract the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-ve-found:710fa11f4f3f3f0cce2973e996c8d4f3&#34;&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve found&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/eliteHRV.png&#34; alt=&#34;EliteHRV&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been taking my HRV every morning for about 3 months now, and the results are interesting. I&amp;rsquo;ve found some great correlation with my training, and sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s obvious to see that I can push further. However, the effect on my joints in response to pushing further in my training will still cause issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand some results have been hard to explain. One anomaly came about when I had super high HRV reading, but the Elite HRV readiness reading was red. This was confusing, because as I explained before, the higher your HRV, the better. However, as we can see, this is not always the case. We know many different things can have an effect on the reading, but in this instance, the effect was unknown. I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel too different; maybe a bad night&amp;rsquo;s sleep but nothing too drastic. I did repeat tests to ensure that it was correct and all 3 tests produced  similar results. So either there was a bug in the software or I really was run down. The lesson to be learnt here is to take HRV as a gentle guide but not a complete solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The gradual training plan </title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/trainingPlan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 11:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/trainingPlan/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve not read my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/content/blog/intro.md&#34;&gt;first few posts&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;d suggest moving back and going through these first. This will give you a basis on why this plan is focused on specific training and gradual build up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will take you through the outline of my training plan, in which I will be strict with pacing and distance, ensuring not to over do it at any point. Please note that I already have a good base for running, therefore it would be advisable to scale up/down the distances for your own needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you would expect the main focus of the plan to be about running this is not the case. The plan dictates that I will be active 6 days of the week with 1 day of rest.  This may sound like a lot, but it&amp;rsquo;s important to note the intensity of most of these days. Out of all the days, I would say that only 1 of the days is strenuously intensive.  Also, this is highly based around my own situation where I am static most of the day as I have a desk job. Therefore taking the time out my day to exercise is very important for my health both physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Tuesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Thursday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Friday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Saturday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Sunday&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBH 4km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Stregth - upper body&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Threshold 5km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - yoga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Active&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBL Run 9Km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Lower body&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBH 4km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Yoga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Intervals&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Upper body&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBL Run 10Km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Yoga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBH 4km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Core&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Intervals&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Active&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBL Run 10Km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBH 3Km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - upper Body&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Threshold 5Km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Strength - Yoga&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;BBL 11km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows the first 4 weeks of the plan and from the previous post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/content/blog/hrTraining.md&#34;&gt;heart rate training&lt;/a&gt; you will know the acronyms BBH (base building high) and BBL (base building low), along with the different sessions like intervals and threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;running:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be setting out by running 3 times a week, which previously to me would have been a heavy running week, but this is my old understanding of running 100% all the time. This is not the case here, as you can see only one run per week is intensive. This is either a threshold workout or interval work out. These have the purpose of building that anaerobic threshold, building strength and therefore upping my overall pace.
The other two running sessions are focusing on base building enhancing my muscular and skeletal make up, thus helping my endurance.  The longer of these 2 are steadily building and will do throughout the plan too, but only doing so conservatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;active:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Active&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around once a week there is a block named active. This is where some type of cross training comes into effect. It&amp;rsquo;s not about having an intensive session again, but just introducing another form of exercise and diversifying.  This help drastically as it ensures that we still have some emphasis on the parts of the body neglected when only running. For myself this will pretty much always be some form of cycling. It&amp;rsquo;ll only be a fairly gentle cycle in and around town, but it will just help get some more miles in the legs, but reducing the impact on my joints etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;strength:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this is a very important point of this plan. Many runners neglect the strength side of training, believing that getting out for an extra run will benefit them more. This is never true and will more than likely result in injury. This is a particular area that I struggle with. However much rigour and determination I have in my running, sometimes this just does not translate over to other areas of my life. So I will be focusing on this area a lot and ensuring I put the effort in to minimise that risk of injury. Also see that the strength routines focus on different areas of the body, to ensure my full body make up is accounted for and nothing become under developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rest:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Rest&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously this means rest. It does not mean sit all day, but it will certainly mean a reduced work load. A little bit of walking around town, but just being mindful not to over excerpt yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;other:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Other&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that has not been noted down in this plan is stretching. I am not an avid stretcher, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/the-running-blog/2013/oct/10/should-you-stretch-before-running&#34;&gt;especially not before a run&lt;/a&gt;. But I do sometimes do some at night, usually after a running day and also use foam rollers and massage balls. I feel this is important to ensure you keep a good range of motion and also it help you listen to your body a little more. You start to feel where you are tight, which areas of the body will cause injury soon. I can&amp;rsquo;t stress enough the importance of knowing injury symptoms.  The problem/painful area is more often than not the cause of the issue, in a lot of issues the problem are is usually further up the chain. Like knee problems being hip and glut issues. And hip flex strains being core strength issues. I would highly advise you see physio&amp;rsquo;s to talk through any pains or niggles you have and ensure you have a good stretching and strengthening plan. And like me, after this point you get to know your body and warning signs so well, then you know exactly what the issues is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/stretchingMan.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;stretching man&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;future:dbfb854646dfbb4906bcbd47f0311d2b&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now, I have actually completed these first 4 weeks of training and I&amp;rsquo;m really glad to say they have gone very well. I&amp;rsquo;m injury free, other than a few small niggles, but nothing that will stop me. Between the 2 threshold sessions I managed to shave off 6 seconds/km which is very substantial and generally I&amp;rsquo;m feeling much better. Day to day, I feel far from the illness that started 5 months ago and hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll continue on this projection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 4 weeks are roughly the same as you&amp;rsquo;ve seen above only upping the distances. 1 of the weeks I will be running 4 times, which will be interesting to see how my body reacts in terms of any inflammation etc. And at the end of this cycle I should be at  around 15km for my long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--stackedit_data:
eyJoaXN0b3J5IjpbMTA2MzY2MTMxMF19
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heart rate training</title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/hrTraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/hrTraining/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in the introductory blog post, I often find I push myself far too much. Every training run turns into some sort of challenge, either it being upping my average pace, pushing my fastest kilometer or the demon that is Strava segments. You can&amp;rsquo;t tell me that when you post a segment near the top of the leader board you aren&amp;rsquo;t proud. But this all becomes part of the problem. Most of your training should not be done at pace, it should be a balance and I need to readdress this somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/heartRate.png&#34; alt=&#34;heart rate&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heart-rate:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Heart Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various methods of regulating energy output during a run. Monitoring pace, breathing, mentally perceived expenditure or even something that&amp;rsquo;s being borrowed from the cycling world, power output.  But I decided I&amp;rsquo;d explore a tried and tested method of heart rate (HR) monitoring whilst running. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying this is better than any other, but offers me the opportunity to break down my energy output in numbers that will give me guidance and also hard and fast rules to ensure I am not over training/overreaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;heart-rate-zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Heart rate zones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most literature, HR training is broken down into percentage zones of the maximum HR. Training runs are then based on these zones to give the correct intensity for the activity. This is great because it makes the analysis and energy expenditure agnostic to the environment you are training in, although this is sometimes disputed and I will talk about this later. Pace should no longer be a figure to analyse during the activity, which is good because then you minimise the possibility of over training, a problem I often had.  Although obviously comparing your pace over time can give you some indications of fitness, it is still subject to abnormalities such as terrain, climate, current health etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;calculate-zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Calculate Zones&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is to work out your heart rate or each zone. There is no easy way of doing this, but there are simple approximations we can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;resting-hr:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Resting HR&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First find your resting heart rate. Over a couple of days, take your &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polar.com/blog/how-to-measure-resting-heart-rate/&#34;&gt;heart rate right after waking up&lt;/a&gt; and before you start rushing around for the day. The average of this gives your resting HR. Mine is around 50 bpm which is fairly low so do not be alarmed if yours is higher than this, on average people have resting HR&amp;rsquo;s of around 60 - 100 bpm. This is also a fairly decent metric to keep track of as it is a relatively good indicator of fitness, the lower your resting HR the fitter you are, but always be aware of other serious heart issues causing a radical change in resting heart rates and also illness based changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;max-hr:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Max HR&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to find your maximum HR. A crude example of this is to do 211 - (0.64 * your age). Therefore mine is :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;211 - (0.64 * 29) = 192&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Zones&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could use the calculator to then work out the HR zones, but it&amp;rsquo;s just a bit easier to jump onto this website and enter your information. &lt;a href=&#34;I have no affiliation with the website, it&#39;s just a nice interface&#34;&gt;HR Zones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have our zones lets see what this means. I&amp;rsquo;ll use my figures as examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Zone&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Percentage of Max HR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Activity Info&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;My HR (bpm)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;50 - 60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Warm up / Cool down&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;121 - 135&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;60 - 70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Aerobic exercise fat burning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;135 - 149&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;70 - 80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Aerobic to Anaerobic Crossover&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;149 - 164&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;80 - 90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Anaerobic Carb burning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;164 - 178&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;90 - 100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Full tilt 10 - 20 second max&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;178 - 192&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So previously when I was becoming injured a fair bit, I was pushing myself into zone 4 continuously, which was causing lots of stress on my body on a regular occurrence and as you can imagine this is not a great idea. It takes time to recover from this excursion not to mention the inflammation on the joints, muscles and anything interconnected. So ensuring that we mix up our training zones are a must for long term fitness. To do this, the following training runs are defined to help schedule your running log.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-types:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Training types&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;base-building:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Base building&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I split this term into two types. Base building low (BBL) and base building high (BBH). Essentially this is restricting yourself zones 1 and 2, but I split this a little more to say I will concentrate on staying towards the crossover of 1 and 2 for BBL and towards the top end of 2 for BBH dependent on the distance. This type of training does exactly what it says, it is building your base. So priming your body to run longer distances, increasing the muscle memory of running and improving the efficiency of your fat metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;threshold:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Threshold&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A threshold run is designed to improve your anaerobic abilities, and we achieve this by dipping just into the anaerobic zone,  sticking towards the top end of zone 3. This is for those short blasts, practicing at near race pace, but just without the big adrenaline kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;interval:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Interval&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many names for this, but intervals are the best name for it as you are, well, running really fast, at set intervals. There are lots of configurations of intervals, but they all consist of pushing into zones 4 and 5 and then dropping back down to zone 2 intermittently.  This again will improve your anaerobic abilities along with building a little more strength into your runs. This is important when wanting to add pace into your running life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great, we now have much better way of defining our runs in way which is agnostic to your environment. So we can decide to do BBL 10km one day and still know we will not be too fatigued to carry on with the day and even exercise the next day. Whereas we know if we are set to do a 5km threshold run we are starting to push our limits and will need time to rest afterwards. It would be advisable to be fairly sedentary for the rest of the day and also take it easy if you have any exercise planned the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hr-drift:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;HR Drift&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I notice when I first started to use this method was that throughout my run my HR started to drift, even though my perceived effort and pace was still stable. Because of this, on my BB and Threshold runs I keep a track of my HR percentage over the first 10 mins, in which you should reach a stable state, and then attempt to keep the same perceived output throughout the remainder of the run, or keep at roughly the same pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest I am not completely sure that this is right idea, but it is what is working for me right now. You can read up on this &lt;a href=&#34;http://running.competitor.com/2014/05/training/the-effect-of-cardiac-drift-on-heart-rate-training_48317/2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and also searching around the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.illnesstoultra.com/img/heartRatePaceCompare.png&#34; alt=&#34;heart rate graph&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;next:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a good knowledge of types of runs based around the HR monitoring method. We can go forward and create a training plan around this. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ll be discussing in my next blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--stackedit_data:
eyJoaXN0b3J5IjpbLTE1MzA2NzUxMjFdfQ==
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>intro</title>
      <link>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.illnesstoultra.com/blog/intro/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to start this blog for many reasons. First it will be a great catalyst for me to achieve something I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about for a while now.  Also, I would like to try and document the problems I come across when training and also away from training because I do not believe I follow the status quo.  The aim of this is to push people into thinking about their own training and personal health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ultra:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Ultra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as you will have guessed from the blog name, I&amp;rsquo;m looking to do an Ultra (any run over the marathon distance) someday. I&amp;rsquo;ve become interested in this area of running firstly after being out on the hills in the UK and then later moving to NZ and meeting some very inspirational people.  It still amazes me how very normal people can push their body into this epic achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the other part of the blog title mentions, I got pretty ill recently. Nobody really has any idea what or why this happened which really unnerves me, but I believe my only solution now is to listen to my body a little more and attempt to understand what went wrong in the first place. I will be exploring this slightly in this blog via nutrition and lifestyle, which also tie in very well with training again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;me-you:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Me / You&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have a basis for the subject of the blog let&amp;rsquo;s now look at me, and how I may resonate with any of your issues and traits in your life. This will mainly be the reason I expect people to reading this and hopefully it will become a great reference you can take and manipulate to adapt to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I have always been a runner. My mother and father are also runners and they used to take me to meet ups every week from being a toddler. I then progressed into racing what felt like every weekend throughout my youth, but this was always interspersed with other sports and fitness related activities. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been above average, but never at a standard that would stand out or was worth pursuing in any way. So this is one area where I believe puts me at a great advantage (and sometimes a disadvantage) over many other runners. I am used to pushing myself when running, I feel it comes naturally and I crave for that challenge when I run. This is different to the contrast you see in most people where they struggle to find the mental aptitude to push themselves.  Which means the issues they face are the complete opposite from my own, and I often find that this is what most content, either via blogs, magazines or even word of mouth focuses on. Therefore I often come away feeling completely disengaged from the information given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;overtraining:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Overtraining&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to my lust for pushing myself I often find myself injured. I always feel like I have some type of niggle and anytime anyone asks me how my runnings going it&amp;rsquo;s always going to be, &amp;ldquo;well I tweaked my {insert body part} the other day&amp;rdquo;. I used to a be a regular to the physio when trying to beat my boss in the next 10km. One day I decided to get up early before work and attempt to do a marathon, because well, I&amp;rsquo;d never run that far before. Safe to say I got to the half distance before I had to limp home because my knee seized up. Sometimes this does pay off, for example I managed to cycle 200 miles in a day with my friend. Just because we could. This is all the cause of stubbornness and not understanding the current limits of my body. So this is one area I hope to change a lot. I want to implement a strict training plan and STICK TO IT! I&amp;rsquo;ve never been good with this in the past, so I will be making use of data and visibility to force myself into this routine. More on this in subsequent posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;goals:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining an Ultra as a personal goal is no small claim, but as many people have shown before it&amp;rsquo;s more than doable and it is just a case of being methodical and patient. First of all I need to regularly get over the half marathon distance, and being that 30km is my longest ever run I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to start small and work up. This is something I&amp;rsquo;ll explore further in posts to come, where I&amp;rsquo;ll list minor goals along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope that gives a general outline of what to expect from the blog and hopefully I can put together some useful content that people can draw upon the information to build their own training plan and make small changes to their lives.
&lt;!--stackedit_data:
eyJoaXN0b3J5IjpbLTIzNDA0NTc0M119
--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>