<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Illness to Ultra</title>
    <link>https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Illness to Ultra</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:29:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Heart rate training</title>
      <link>https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/hrTraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/hrTraining/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in the introductory blog post, I often find I push myself far too much. Every training run turns into some sort of challenge, either it being upping my average pace, pushing my fastest kilometer or the demon that is Strava segments. You can&amp;rsquo;t tell me that when you post a segment near the top of the leader board you aren&amp;rsquo;t proud. But this all becomes part of the problem. Most of your training should not be done at pace, it should be a balance and I need to readdress this somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heart-rate:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Heart Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various methods of regulating energy output during a run. Monitoring pace, breathing, mentally perceived expenditure or even something that&amp;rsquo;s being borrowed from the cycling world, power output.  But I decided I&amp;rsquo;d explore a tried and tested method of heart rate (HR) monitoring whilst running. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying this is better than any other, but offers me the opportunity to break down my energy output in numbers that will give me guidance and also hard and fast rules to ensure I am not over training/overreaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;heart-rate-zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Heart rate zones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most literature, HR training is broken down into percentage zones of the maximum HR. Training runs are then based on these zones to give the correct intensity for the activity. This is great because it makes the analysis and energy expenditure agnostic to the environment you are training in, although this is sometimes disputed and I will talk about this later. Pace should no longer be a figure to analyse during the activity, which is good because then you minimise the possibility of over training, a problem I often had.  Although obviously comparing your pace over time can give you some indications of fitness, it is still subject to abnormalities such as terrain, climate, current health etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;calculate-zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Calculate Zones&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is to work out your heart rate or each zone. There is no easy way of doing this, but there are simple approximations we can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;resting-hr:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Resting HR&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First find your resting heart rate. Over a couple of days, take your heart rate 5-10 minutes after waking up and before you start rushing around for the day. The average of this gives your resting HR. Mine is around 50 bpm which is fairly low so do not be alarmed if yours is higher than this, on average people have resting HR&amp;rsquo;s of around 60 - 100 bpm. This is also a fairly decent metric to keep track of as it is a relatively good indicator of fitness, the lower your resting HR the fitter you are, but always be aware of other serious heart issues causing a radical change in resting heart rates and also illness based changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;max-hr:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Max HR&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to find your maximum HR. A crude example of this is to do 211 - (0.64 * your age). Therefore mine is :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;211 - (0.64 * 29) = 192&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;zones:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Zones&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could use the calculator to then work out the HR zones, but it&amp;rsquo;s just a bit easier to jump onto this website and enter your information. &lt;a href=&#34;I have no affiliation with the website, it&#39;s just a nice interface&#34;&gt;HR Zones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have our zones lets see what this means. I&amp;rsquo;ll use my figures as examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Zone&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Percentage of Max HR&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Activity Info&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;My HR (bpm)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;50 - 60&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Warm up / Cool down&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;121 - 135&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;60 - 70&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Aerobic exercise fat burning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;135 - 149&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;70 - 80&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Aerobic to Anaerobic Crossover&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;149 - 164&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;80 - 90&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Anaerobic Carb burning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;164 - 178&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;90 - 100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Full tilt 10 - 20 second max&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;178 - 192&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So previously when I was becoming injured a fair bit, I was pushing myself into zone 4 continuously, which was causing lots of stress on my body on a regular occurrence and as you can imagine this is not a great idea. It takes time to recover from this excursion not to mention the inflammation on the joints, muscles and anything interconnected. So ensuring that we mix up our training zones are a must for long term fitness. To do this, the following training runs are defined to help schedule your running log.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-types:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Training types&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;base-building:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Base building&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I split this term into two types. Base building low (BBL) and base building high (BBH). Essentially this is restricting yourself zones 1 and 2, but I split this a little more to say I will concentrate on staying towards the crossover of 1 and 2 for BBL and towards the top end of 2 for BBH dependent on the distance. This type of training does exactly what it says, it is building your base. So priming your body to run longer distances, increasing the muscle memory of running and improving the efficiency of your fat metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;threshold:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Threshold&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A threshold run is designed to improve your anaerobic abilities, and we achieve this by dipping just into the anaerobic zone,  sticking towards the top end of zone 3. This is for those short blasts, practicing at near race pace, but just without the big adrenaline kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;interval:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Interval&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many names for this, but intervals are the best name for it as you are, well, running really fast, at set intervals. There are lots of configurations of intervals, but they all consist of pushing into zones 4 and 5 and then dropping back down to zone 2 intermittently.  This again will improve your anaerobic abilities along with building a little more strength into your runs. This is important when wanting to add pace into your running life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is great, we now have much better way of defining our runs in way which is agnostic to your environment. So we can decide to do BBL 10km one day and still know we will not be too fatigued to carry on with the day and even exercise the next day. Whereas we know if we are set to do a 5km threshold run we are starting to push our limits and will need time to rest afterwards. It would be advisable to be fairly sedentary for the rest of the day and also take it easy if you have any exercise planned the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hr-drift:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;HR Drift&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I notice when I first started to use this method was that throughout my run my HR started to drift, even though my perceived effort and pace was still stable. Because of this, on my BB and Threshold runs I keep a track of my HR percentage over the first 10 mins, in which you should reach a stable state, and then attempt to keep the same perceived output throughout the remainder of the run, or keep at roughly the same pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest I am not completely sure that this is right idea, but it is what is working for me right now. You can read up on this &lt;a href=&#34;http://running.competitor.com/2014/05/training/the-effect-of-cardiac-drift-on-heart-rate-training_48317/2&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and also searching around the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;next:e68968a8cca61b1e1121a0b5846a5786&#34;&gt;Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a good knowledge of types of runs based around the HR monitoring method. We can go forward and create a training plan around this. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ll be discussing in my next blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>intro</title>
      <link>https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nickwinder.github.io/illness-to-ultra/blog/intro/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to start this blog for many reasons. First it will be a great catalyst for me to achieve something I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about for a while now.  Also, I would like to try and document the problems I come across when training and also away from training because I do not believe I follow the status quo.  The aim of this is to push people into thinking about their own training and personal health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ultra:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Ultra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as you will have guessed from the blog name, I&amp;rsquo;m looking to do an Ultra (any run over the marathon distance) someday. I&amp;rsquo;ve become interested in this area of running firstly after been out on the hills in the UK and then later moving to NZ and meeting some very inspirational people.  It still amazes me how very normal people can push their body into this epic achievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illness:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Illness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the other part of the blog title mentions, I got pretty ill recently. I/anyone really has any idea what or why this happened which really unnerves me, but I believe my only solution now is to listen to my body a little more and attempt to understand what went wrong in the first place. I will be exploring this slightly in this blog via nutrition and lifestyle, which also tie in very well with training again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;me-you:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Me / You&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have a basis for the subject of the blog let&amp;rsquo;s now look at me, and how I may resonate with any of your issues and traits in your life. This will mainly be the reason I expect people to reading this and hopefully it will become a great reference you can take and manipulate to adapt to your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I have always been a runner. My mother and father are also runners and they used to take me to meet ups every week from being a toddler. I then progressed into racing what felt like every weekend throughout my youth, but this was always interspersed with other sports and fitness related activities. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been above average, but never at a standard that would stand out or was worth pursuing in any way. So this is one area where I believe puts me at a great advantage (and sometimes a disadvantage) over many other runners. I am used to pushing myself when running, I feel it comes naturally and I crave for that challenge when I run. This is different to the contrast you see in most people where they struggle to find the mental aptitude to push themselves.  Which means the issues they face are the complete opposite from my own, and I often find that this is what most content, either via blogs, magazines or even word of mouth focuses on. Therefore I often come away feeling completely disengaged from the information given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;overtraining:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Overtraining&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to my lust for pushing myself I often find myself injured. I always feel like I have some type of niggle and anytime anyone asks me how my runnings going it&amp;rsquo;s always going to be, &amp;ldquo;well I tweaked my {insert body part} the other day&amp;rdquo;. I used to a be a regular to the physio when trying to beat my boss in the next 10km. One day I decided to get up early before work and attempt to do a marathon, because well, I&amp;rsquo;d never run that far before. Safe to say I got to the half distance before I had to limp home because my knee seized up. Sometimes this does pay off, for example I managed to cycle 200 miles in a day with my friend. Just because we could. This is all the cause of stubbornness and not understanding the current limits of my body. So this is one area I hope to change a lot. I want to implement a strict training plan and STICK TO IT! I&amp;rsquo;ve never been good with this in the past, so I will be making use of data and visibility to force myself into this routine. More on this in subsequent posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;goals:34c4da6d4768d05e50db99357a299b5c&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining an Ultra as a personal goal is no small claim, but as many people have shown before it&amp;rsquo;s more than doable and it is just a case of being methodical and patient. First of all I need to regularly get over the half marathon distance, and being that 30km is my longest ever run I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to start small and work up. This is something I&amp;rsquo;ll explore further in posts to come, where I&amp;rsquo;ll list minor goals along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope that gives a general outline of what to expect from the blog and hopefully I can put together some useful content that people can draw upon the information to build their own training plan and make small changes to their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>